frog pumps are an amazing glute exercise
they're very safe when done right they
lead to very high glute activation
levels there are very effective ways to
load it and in around one of five people
due to individual differences in hip
anatomy it lights up their glutes like
no other exercise
i'm one of those people nothing works my
glutes as well as frog pumps
i love body weight frog pumps i love
dumbbell frog pumps i love smith machine
frog pumps i love partner frog pumps
in this video i'm going to teach you how
to frock pump i'm going to break down
the science for you
and i'm going to show you how we do it
at glue lab
okay frog pumps first let me give you
the history when i was coming up in the
fitness industry
a guy by the name of james smitty diesel
he came up with a very interesting hip
thrust variation he trained male
athletes and he'd
have like a triangle and he'd have his
guys put their feet
on the triangle their knees would be
splayed out
and they would do banded hip thrusts
that way i remember one day he said hey
you know can you measure this can you
measure the glute activation because
my guys are loving it so this was back
in probably like 2013 i would say
and i remember looking at it going that
looks stupid thereby
doing exactly what people do to me with
my exercise they look at it they go that
looks stupid you know powerlifting bros
they'll look at my stuff in the back
that looks dumb just squat
just deadlift don't put your back on a
bench and hump the air quit doing your
your [__] abduction movements and just
squat like a man
you serious i hate that attitude and i
did the same thing to smitty and what's
sad is i really respected smitty he was
one of the top three most innovative
guys in the industry in my opinion so
he's kind of the founder of the frog
pump but he didn't name it that
and i forgot all about his variation and
one day i'm reading a research paper
and it's talking about how hip abduction
and hip external rotation
both increase glute activity compared to
staying in neutral
in the study they were prone they were
laying face down and it looked weird
and i thought that would be really weird
doing a kickback trying to abduct and
externally rotate it just didn't look
natural
so sitting there you know the wheels
were turning and i'm like i wonder if
you could do that supine i wonder what
that would look like if you flipped
around so i immediately went out to my
garage got on my back put my feet
together
and started bridging and i was like oh
my god this works great i remember i had
a friend visiting me we were supposed to
go to dinner and i'm like hey will you
record me real quick i'm gonna post this
video to youtube
the date was june 3rd 2015 and within 20
minutes i had posted the video youtube
and wrote up a quick blog post about it
and
people went crazy people went crazy over
the frog pump i couldn't believe it back
then we just did body weight and i got
better and better at frog pumps and i
remember getting the point where i could
do a couple sets of 100 reps and so a
lot of popular women back then started
doing them nightly you know like a few
times a week they'd throw in their
two or three sets of 100 frog pumps now
i should mention that i don't feel
frog pumps until like rep 60 and then
from like 60 to 80 it's burning so bad
in them and then if i go from 80 to 100
it's like
the most excruciating burn i've ever
experienced what's interesting about
this
is that pretend i never saw smitty's
variation this would have been one
instance where
research drove innovation in the field
you know usually it's the other way
around it's we people in the field the
trainers the coaches
we figure stuff out and then the
scientists decide to study that but this
time i got the idea from a research
paper and it caused me to think of
something in the gym
[Applause]
pretty cool because it rarely works that
way interestingly i was left with a
dilemma do i call these frog pumps or do
i call them like butterfly pumps you
might have went with butterfly pumps
because your legs are splayed out
in a butterfly position but i went with
frog pumps and i don't regret it check
out these grilled frog legs here look at
the glutes on these frogs
clearly the frog pump works i'm being
sarcastic that was a joke but frog pumps
do have jack glutes now i want to tell
you about the craziest glute pump i've
ever achieved so back in that era this
is
uh this is phoenix garage gym phoenix
glute lab i made a really funny post
i would basically have my girlfriend at
the time stand over me and film me
while i looked straight in the camera
and did frog pumps and i just
lock eyes with the camera wouldn't blink
and i just do frog pumps and people
loved it and i wanted to do it to this
song call on me
and the reason why is because the video
for call on me had this guy in like an
aerobics room doing all these sexual
moves they were doing glute bridges and
things like that and i always liked the
video
so i downloaded that song but i think it
was like the techno remix version
because it took a long time for the beat
to drop so i get down on the floor
you know i play this song and i have my
girlfriend standing over
recording me and i'm pumping away
waiting for the drop and i get to like
120 reps and i realize
man i undershot that big time so i redid
it got back down on the ground fast
forward the song and i did the same
thing
i undershot it and i ended up doing like
120 frog pumps and the beat still didn't
drop
and it's nice because when the beat
kicks in i get this frog pump
to the beat you know you're like boom
boom boom
boom just one frog pump a second you
know so i did it a third time this time
i nailed it
but once the beat kicked in i wanted to
do more reps so i ended up doing about
three sets of 120.
i got up and my glutes had like locked
shut i couldn't i couldn't walk i had to
walk twisting side to side because my
hip wouldn't extend my glutes were that
pump
[Music]
and to this day it's the craziest glute
pump i've ever achieved as the frog pump
climbed the ranks and got more popular
you'd see the comments like oh my god
these are amazing oh my god i
can't believe how effective this is and
then i start to notice people being like
i don't get it i don't feel these
am i doing something wrong now i will
say that probably around
half the people that tell me they can't
feel them they just need adjustments
with their form you know i need to work
with their stance their level of
abduction etc and i'll show you how to
do that in a minute but around a third
of people
just don't feel frog pumps no matter
what they try and it's not their fault
it's not that they're doing it wrong
it's due to their hip anatomy
i like to use my client kiana's example
because kiana has
incredible glute development when she
squats you know when she hip thrust she
takes a narrow stance and she actually
likes
turning her feet inwards a little bit
but she walks that way she has a natural
kind of hip internal rotation and you
can
you can actually feel when you palpate
you can feel her glutes working way
harder this way
compared to when she has a wide stance
or when she turns her feet out so
abduction and extra rotation doesn't
work for her hip anatomy whereas with my
hips you know i walk with my feet turned
out my whole family does
my hips are externally rotated naturally
so the frog pumps feel so good they feel
so normal to me they feel so natural to
me so it's the same with squat stance
some people like it wider than others
some people flare their feet out more
than others but it's even more
pronounced with bridges so if you're one
of those frog pump non-responders just
don't do them they're not for you but
before you conclude that please try a
few things which i'll show you in a
little bit now this was over five years
ago now a professor at asu
her name was aaron pfizer she and i
collaborated on experiment and we were
going to publish it but i'm just
too scatterbrained i don't know why i
don't publish it i should now you know
we got ethics approval
we just need to write it up and publish
it i think it'd be a very
useful study to publish especially in
physical therapy but also
probably has ramifications for
hypertrophy training all right so here's
what aaron and i did we took
13 highly trained women you know these
were my clients they have at least a
couple years of legit
training experience and we had them do
six different types of glute bridges
okay we had electrodes on the upper and
lower gluteus maximus and we had them do
10 reps and we looked the average
electromyographic activity the average
emg activity throughout those 10 reps we
had them do a normal stance which was
hip width we did a normal
abducted where you took your normal
stance but you let your knees come out a
little bit we did a wide stance which
was twice hip width or double the width
of the normal stance now
we also added a band to that and did
banded wide stance this was a mini bed
placed around the knees and then finally
we did frog pumps
feet together and then max contraction
where you take your normal stance and
then squeeze your glutes as hard as
possible now i would have predicted
that the max contraction variation would
have gotten the highest upper and lower
glute activation because you're
squeezing as hard as you can but
interestingly that wasn't the case the
wide banded variation got the highest
glute activity because
you know you're pushing out against
those bands apparently that exceeds what
you can do on your own when you squeeze
so upper gluteus maximus was the wide
banded followed by
max contraction which makes sense out of
those six variations one of them
involves resistance you know with the
band
another involves squeezing the muscles
as hard as possible kind of artificially
using the mind muscle connection and the
other four are just normal stances you
know you know narrow stance narrow
abducted
wide and frog pump so with the
unweighted normal stances frog pumps
topped the chart okay frog pumps for
upper glutes beat out
a wide stance which i wasn't sure if it
would it beat out
the narrow abducted stance and it beat
out the narrow stance now for lower
gluteus maximus
max contraction topped the charts but
then frog pumps were in second place so
frog pumps beat out the banded variation
and they also beat out
wide abducted and narrow stance so out
of the four different
stances without using resistance frog
pumps appear to be the best way to
bridge
and the least effective way to bridge at
least on average
is a narrow stance so i've done this
drill at probably 50 seminars
in the last decade and i have people try
out all sorts of stances and probably 30
of these times i've had like 100 people
in the room you know every time i give a
seminar i have people do all these
bridge variations and i say raise your
hand if you like this the most or raise
your hand if you feel this more than the
last variation and i've done it so often
that i could predict around a third of
the room will raise their hand on this
one
you know two-thirds of the room will
raise their hands on this one and this
drill is so powerful because it shows
you the importance of
individual differences and tailoring
exercise selection to the uniqueness of
the individual because what you'll find
is with a hundred people the results are
all across the board you know you have
some people who
the narrow stance is their favorite
variation but it's only like ten out of
a hundred you know a lot of people wide
stance is their favorite variation they
feel that in the glutes the most some
people like narrow abducted and then
you'll get around 30 to 50 percent of
people who say the frog pump was their
favorite variation but then you say you
know how many people
felt that the frog pump was their least
favorite variation where they felt the
glutes the least and you get a lot of
people raising their hand
and that's because it really targets
people with certain hip anatomies
all right now i'm gonna go through the
technique okay so you're gonna start on
your back okay
you're gonna put your feet together and
you're gonna pull your feet close to
your butt
i see a lot of people doing it with
their feet far away you don't want that
you'll feel that more in the hamstrings
you want your feet dragged back towards
your butt okay
now you can put your head flat on the
ground but i like it more
when you tuck your chin into your chest
and if this fatigues your neck muscles
you can just elevate your head onto a
bosu ball i always joke that this is the
best use for the boso ball is for frog
pumps and the reason why we tuck the
chin is this prevents you from
hyperextending the spine all right now
the most important thing is your level
of hip abduction okay there's some
clients that can take their legs
all the way to the ground it's almost
like they could do like a reverse
push-up type thing lift their butt off
the ground by abducting
even if you can go that far you don't go
that far okay you use about two-thirds
of your available abduction range of
motion so say your legs can go to here
you bring them up and you go from about
here but this is one element that you
really need to experiment because
everyone's different some people like to
abduct more than others but you're not
you're definitely not going to the
maximum here now i kind of do two
different types of frog pumps you know i
do them where i kind of just pump away
and i may not get full hip extension on
every single rep but i'm using
repetition
to get a huge glute pump the other way
is to make sure you get
total full hip extension on every rep
and you kind of squeeze
extra at the top it's almost like a
little pause now i don't pause for like
a one second count but you you just make
sure you top out
on every single rep and when i do it the
first way my sets might be 100 to 120
for the first set then you know
80 to 100 for the second set and then
like 60 to 80 for the third set right i
get more reps when i do it the second
way
i might do like 80 60 40. it decreases
the reps i can do by about 20. now as i
said earlier you won't feel your glutes
during the first like
30 reps you know if you're conditioned
you're used to training glutes it's
going to take some reps but don't worry
before the set ends you'll likely be
burning like crazy now it helps to have
your head on a bosu ball or just be on a
surface that has a lot of friction if
you start sliding backwards then your
leg angle
opens up your knee angle opens up and
then you start feeling it more in the
hammies so sometimes you have to
readjust and
bring your feet back in towards your
butt so bodyweight frog pumps are great
but what's even better
are loaded frog pumps and i'm going to
show you the three main ways
we load the frog pump okay the first way
is with a heavy dumbbell now
this fascinates me okay i can do a 150
pound
frog pump for about 60 reps what's funny
is so can my clients
women tend to have crazy glute endurance
you know i can hip thrust more than most
of them except carly but they can match
me in frog pump wraps even with 150
pound dumbbell now i'm going to show you
how to get in position with a heavy
dumbbell i first thought of this
back in a phoenix gym that had 150 pound
dumbbells and i hated
getting this thing onto my lap so i
realized if i just had the dumbbell
stacked vertically on the ground
i would twist my body onto my side and
then
roll back into position and let the
dumbbell fall across my lap
then same thing with dismounting it you
just roll it over
lay it down and over end so it's stacked
vertically
and this was a game changer because now
i have women doing heavy frog pumps i
had
carly i had sarah i had hannah i had
ashley i had karine
that's six different ladies that could
frog pump 150 pounds
for 50 plus reps then one day i'm
sitting in glute lab and i figure out a
way to do glute bridges off the smith
machine you just do them off a bench and
it dawned on me why don't we frog pump
that way
at that time the smith machine frog pump
was born now
there are vertical smith machines and
then they're angled smith machines when
you hit dress off an angled smith
machine
you want the bar moving this way moving
forward as you come up so if it's angled
this way
you put the bench here with frog pumps
if it's angled this way you lay this way
you lay the opposite way as you do with
hip thrust because when your frog
pimples you come up you're gonna the bar
will come towards you a little bit and i
actually prefer the angled smith machine
over the vertical smith machine or frog
pumps and my girls got very strong at
these as well you know you know they
might bust out a plate on each side for
a set of 50.
two plates on each side for a set of 30
and then three plates on each side
for a set of 15 to 20. my squat is
freakishly strong i bet carly could do
three plates on each side for 50 reps i
think i do
35 reps with six plates for a couple of
sets and then i move up to four plates
per side
and bust out 20 reps and if i just do
those two sets
my glutes are so pumped i'm walking
around the gym like frankenstein so the
smith machine frog pump was a game
changer and then during covid i started
prescribing partner frog pumps to people
now with the partner frog pumps
you lay down on a bench you have someone
straddle your hips but you want to make
sure you're frog pumping their whole
weight
so the partner can kind of put their
hands on the on your knees if they want
to stabilize themselves you want the
partner to lean back a little bit but
they're going to lift their legs up
and you're going to hold their legs
while you frog pump i know i know
now i've topped the charts every year i
out do myself right
first it was hip thrusts then frog pumps
then some of these abduction movements
like the band supine hip abduction then
it was the partner hip thrust
and now the partner frog pumps it can't
get much more raunchy than this i get it
but seriously
i think we all learned during the
quarantine that it sucks not having a
gym and if you have a partner you know
say
you have a girlfriend that weighs 130
pounds i can frog pump them for three
sets of 50 reps my
boots are on fire they're pumped to the
max i don't care if it seems raunchy
if it's your girlfriend go have at it
you know and you know if it's a very
strong woman and you're with a normal
sized man
you can frog pump him i weigh 250 pounds
and my stronger girls can frog pump me
for like 30 reps you know
all right so please don't judge i don't
care what something looks like
all i care about is helping you get your
best glutes possible so this is the next
best thing
to having actual weights and resistance
so i've taught you how to hip thrust
i explained the science i showed you the
different methods please give frog pumps
a try
do them how i show in this video you
know use resistance go to failure and
see if you like them but don't just
glance at these and just assume that
they're silly like i did with smitty
years ago because most things that get
popular
get popular for a reason you know people
like them but if you don't feel frog
pumps and you've done them as i teach
them
you've tried my methods and don't worry
about it don't ever do frog pumps and
the last thing i want to mention is
safety
you know since 2015 so for six straight
years i've had people frog pumping like
crazy in my gym
no one's ever gotten hurt from them not
a single person if someone was like
these don't feel good on my hips you
just don't have them do them if someone
was like you know i feel these all in my
adductors or these don't feel right then
you modify it you don't have them abduct
as much or you just omit it you don't
have the client do that but there are
many people who do like them and there's
some people like me
it's their favorite glute exercise it's
their best variation so that's my
problem with some of these people
bashing hip thrusts you know
i can tell they don't really train
people because if they did they'd know
that some people love them
and they say silly things like it beats
up your sacrum no one gets their sacrum
beat up from hip thrust at least not my
probably 1 000 clients in the last six
years they say it jams your hip joints
no it doesn't if it does you're not
doing them properly you know
people said oh it does you don't get
full hip extension on them who gives a
crap it gets
super high glute activation not every
exercise has to have a full range of
motion but in the literature
abduction extra rotation have been shown
time and time again to increase glute
activity so the brain appears to
send more juice to the muscles when
you're in that shortened glute position
where you abduct and externally rotate
i've
also heard some people say it doesn't
involve hip extension
yes it does you're extending the hips
just in a wide stance position
and i've heard people bash emg and
they've bashed sensation
and that's just silly okay emg is a very
useful tool if you do
if you have electrodes on you do several
different variations of an exercise that
can help you hone in on the best
exercise for a certain purpose like what
activates a certain muscle the best
especially if you have it on the same
loading conditions like
just body weight for all six variations
and bodybuilders have been
preaching the importance of sensation
for decades you know
talking about the mind muscle connection
listen to your body it's gonna tell you
what your best technique what your best
form your best posture your best stance
with and foot flare and things like that
some people out there say this just
works the piriformis anyone who says
that does not understand biomechanics
you know this is hip extension you can
feel the muscle contracting if you doubt
emg
if you doubt sensation just put your
hands on people's glutes and you'll feel
them contracting like crazy and what's
nice is this effectively works the upper
and lower gluteus maximus
in many individuals so there's no
exercise that's for everyone a third of
people will not like the frog pump
two-thirds will and probably a third
we'll just love the frog pump it's gonna
be amazing for their bodies
all right that's a wrap give it a try
and let me know what you think now
before you comment
i hope people read the rest of the
comments and see because if you're gonna
say
this is the worst exercise ever and you
read the comments and you have people
saying i love frog pumps they're one of
my favorites
then you're being egocentric you know i
might not like a certain exercise but if
all my clients love it i'm not gonna say
it's a
crappy exercise i'm gonna say i don't
like it but i know a lot of other people
love it so in the comments section i
hope to see some people saying
love frog pumps been doing them forever
they're one of my go-to you know
they're one of my main go-to exercises
and i'm sure i'll see a lot of people
saying you know i just don't like them i
tried them brett i tried everything he
said but i just don't feel them and
that's fine but don't knock them until
you've tried them okay that's a wrap
thanks for watching please make sure to
give the video a thumbs up
please leave me a comment and make sure
you're subscribed to my channel
i got a lot of good things to come in
[Music]
if you like what you saw in this video
and you want to train under my system
and principles
then i invite you to click on the link
below and subscribe to booty by brett
and join the thousands of other happy
members who are seeing amazing results
[Music]
um